so what step 1 cell phone
[Music]
step to address I had a breakthrough in
my yoga teaching I thought the students
they can make noises of pain and
frustration during the class they just
go
okay please don't forget you're
meditating in a group and be considerate
to the other other people okay
suffer in pain Ichigo Ichie so cool okay
that's my new word for yoga in Chinese
language mutual suffering
when you teach yoga uh sorry when you
teach meditation it's good to know the
traditional warm-up so we'll go through
it in a relaxed way this morning the
traditional warm-up for meditation and
you should learn it and if you're doing
a meditation which is gonna last more
than I'd say 20 minutes or 30 minutes
it's good to do the warm-up so if you're
teaching a group of people meditation if
it's gonna go more than 20 or 30 minutes
I would do the warm-up with them you can
shorten the warm-up if you like the
purpose of the warm-up is like before
you run a race you should warm up your
legs and in in China last month we did a
course on balance and for fun we did
ballet balancing with all the students
and it's very cool and they got ballet
shoes and they got ballet bars and we
did balancing but to do that you have to
warm up first for about half an hour
with yoga or or you will hurt yourself
and it's the same for meditation so
today we're gonna go through the normal
warm warm up the purpose of the warm-up
is called Suk Jong say Suk Jong yeah Suk
Jong means two purposes of the warm-up
number one John is to
clean away big negative seeds that we've
done in the last few days which might
mess up the meditation that's called
Jong and then suck means to inject some
powerful good seeds into our mind before
we start the meditation so they're
preliminaries or the warm-up of the
muscles meditation muscle before
meditation is meant to suck Jung clean
out fresh bad seeds that are influenced
in your mind today this morning and then
start to collect new good seeds that
will help us to have more power during
the meditation so if you do the warm-up
the meditation will go better because we
learned yesterday meditation is also
coming from seeds so if we do some seed
fixing and some quick seed planting just
before the meditation it'll go better so
here we go then the such young process
the warm-up process requires a heavy
karmic object and the heaviest karmic
object is your teacher as you teach a CI
you may or may not be the heart teacher
of the student the student may be will
have a relationship with you where they
feel that you are their heart teacher or
you feel they feel you are there alone
but in many cases you'll be teaching
some of the people or most of the people
in the room maybe they don't know you
yet or they already have a different
heart Lama and this is the system in the
monastery we got I went to twelve
different teachers during the Geisha
course but only one or two of them were
my heart numbers so when you ask the
students to become beginner's luck young
they're gonna have to do it with the
teacher in front of them in their
meditation and I think you can encourage
them to use a teacher who they feel
close to him so it may not be you you
can when you start the sock jam with
your students I would say bring a
teacher to mind someone that you feel a
close connection to and it may not be me
but in your life so far you have met
people who taught you it could be your
mom and dad who are your first grade
teachers and there are certainly great
teachers for everyone even if you didn't
have a good relationship or you don't
have a good relationship now your mom
carried you for nine months risked her
life to give you life and your father
even if he wasn't a great father he
supported the family usually and worked
hard and had many many hard days to
support you so there are your first
grade teachers and it's always
appropriate
during the Suk Jong during the warm up
to bring your father or mother
into the room in your meditation and
with them you can do suck Jung because
they are heavy karmic object hmm then I
like to go through other kinds of
teachers that a person might have you
might have school teachers when you were
young or even up to your college years
some special teachers who helped you a
lot I know I had four or five very
special teachers and you can do Suk Jong
with them you can change the Suk Jong
teacher every day you can do different
teachers or if you feel very close to
one teacher hard teacher you can do the
sub Jeong with them or you can do it
with them most days and then do it with
some other teachers on some days just
for more variety in meditation variety
and meditation as' is good sometimes I
like to tell people you know obviously
there are other teachers in your life
people who taught you your occupation if
you a real estate agent or an investment
manager or you sell cars or you learned
that skill from somebody I know the
diamond business is a very long training
period if you make a mistake you you
lose a lot of money so there were
several people who taught me the
business and they didn't have to teach
me and they were very kind to spend
almost ten years teaching me the
business so probably you have a similar
person in your life who taught you your
job
some people like to bring a teacher into
the room to do the suck John who is a
historical teacher who's already passed
away someone we didn't meet maybe
historical Buddha many Westerners like
to do it with Jesus if you grew up in an
Islam tradition it might be the Prophet
Muhammad so it depends on your
upbringing or who do you feel close to
these are people of the past who were
great teachers and those great teachers
in Buddhism we would say they are
probably Buddhist and they can hear you
they can read your mind now as you start
your meditation so it's very appropriate
to invite them to the room as a heavy
karmic object to do your suck Jung a
final choice for a teacher oh by the way
your family is a great teacher your wife
or your husband especially in the
diamond way teachings your children are
great teachers which all parents know
I've had students who felt very close to
a pet a pet dog or cat and they thought
that those animals were teaching them as
a Buddha so those are also teachers and
that's fine if you want to do suck John
with them final choice is a teacher you
haven't met yet
maybe in this life you haven't yet found
your heart teacher but you want to and
you think you will and you're planting
the seeds by sharing wisdom with other
people who want to hear about it so as
you do the suck jam you could also
invite a teacher that you haven't met
yet and your perfect future teacher and
you can try to imagine what they might
look like or how their face might be in
every case it's tradition that the
teacher with whom you do the suction is
very happy to be invited to this room
this morning
so it's traditional to imagine with your
eyes closed that they are looking at you
with very great love and affection and
they're very proud of you that you have
decided to meditate this morning
keep your meditation commitments and
they're very happy that you invited them
to the room when you teach subject to
your students I think it's very
important to encourage them not to think
of the teacher who's sitting with them
don't think of this teacher as a picture
or a statue
we are not meditating with a piece of
paper or a piece of metal we are
meditating with a real living being so I
find it useful and it's traditional to
imagine their chest rising and falling
with the breath and you can feel the
warmth when they walk in the room
there's
some air moves past you when they sit
down in front of you there's some
disturbance of the air and in Buddhism
there's a tradition that very holy
people good people who are good persons
have a special smell fragrance of their
body it could be like incense or it
could be like a flower it could be like
the ocean but they have a special smell
coming out of their body from their good
deeds people who don't eat meat for a
long time they also have a special sweet
smell so imagine that your teacher is
has this nice smell and they are looking
at you and they're very happy and you
invite them to come sit with you I like
to say knee to knee your knees aren't
almost touching and they're gonna be the
karmic object for your suction the first
warm-up is to greet them and show them
respect you could imagine that you are
prostrating or you could imagine that
you just hold your hands at your heart
the custom of prostration and Buddhism
came from the reaction of a person who
just saw emptiness directly because at
that time you see Buddha directly for
the first time and I would say in every
case that person who saw emptiness
we'll do a full prostration
automatically even if no one ever taught
them where they never saw one so when we
meet our teacher we bow down to them the
reason you prostrate is that you respect
this person something about them is very
special so a mental prostration before
you start meditating is just to think
about something you admire in this
person the word for faith in the ancient
languages Shraddha and the word for how
do we say admiration are the same word
so faith means I'm looking at my teacher
and there's some beautiful quality about
them that I admire and if you think
about it that's why you ask them to
teach you because you want to learn this
quality ideally a teacher is not just
giving you information a teacher is
giving you an example so it's it's a
mental prostration as a warm-up to
meditation to think about some beautiful
quality of this teacher my teacher I can
think of really enjoys helping sick
people old people it spends much of
their day doing that much of their night
doing that and so I'm gonna pause here
these are things to teach your student
if you have time about collecting seeds
to have a power
for meditation five minutes from now and
I'd like you your self today to invite a
teacher to please come in the room to
meditate with you and then I'd like you
to do a mental prostration think of one
quality that you admire about them when
you think about some beautiful thing
about your teacher you are collecting
heavy karmic seeds which will make your
meditation five in ten minutes from now
much more powerful so the quality of
your meditation in this meditation
tradition depends on how clearly you
think about their good qualities and
something about them as a living example
which you would like to learn okay here
we go invite a teacher any teacher who's
close to you and then admire something
about them here we go
the next part of suction or warm-up is
to make an offering to this teacher it's
both gratitude and it's a request I
think as you become a a CI teacher
people may offer you things maybe it
would be a pen or maybe it will be a
house and you will start to understand
more about offering if you're the person
receiving the offering as opposed to the
person giving the offering and I think
when you're a baby teacher when you
first start teaching you really enjoy
things people give you a sweater or
people offer you a special book or a pen
or people give you money offer you money
or even a car or a house or something
big and in the I think as a young
teacher you feel happy you feel some
kind of pride that people are giving
your attention and people are making
your offerings
I'd like to say two things about those
offerings number one they don't last and
they're not very important and often
times the people who make the largest
offerings are expecting something else
from you than teaching they want your
attention
or even your affection there could be
many reasons why people make offerings
to you oftentimes the person who gives
the largest offerings actually wants
something from you
which is not related to teaching and
even if the offering is sincere those
offerings disappear you use them or you
lose them so I think as you I think John
or other Connie other senior teachers
here can tell you those offerings are
not so important it's a good thing to
offer things and it's a good thing to
accept them gracefully and to use them
if it's appropriate but I think as you
get older as a teacher you realize that
the real offering you enjoy from your
students is to see them get happier and
happier is to see their meditation
improving to see their yoga improving to
see their health improving and
especially to see their mind improving
their attitude their patience their
goodness and actually become a teacher
and as the years go by I think your
attention will shift from physical gifts
to enjoying success with your students
enjoying seeing your students become
good people so in the sub Jeong process
is traditional to offer your teacher you
you don't visualize a new house or a new
car
you offer them your improvement and your
practice I'm more patient this year than
last year and I've been trying hard
I haven't succeeded I still have many
faults daily but in general I'm working
hard to be a better person and I offer
to you my small successes so make an
offering this is planting tremendous
seeds for the meditation ten minutes
from now
Suk Jeong we are sucked make that
teacher an offering there's a
Samantabhadra offering where you imagine
the whole sky filled with roses or lotus
flowers all the beautiful cars in the
world and that's okay
if you're in the mood the best coffee
you drink this year some days you can do
that offering but the offering they
really enjoy and the offering you will
enjoy later as a ACI teacher is to see
the student improving and happier
the next part of sub Chang the next part
of the meditation warmup and again as a
teacher or as you lead a meditation you
have to judge how much time you have
whether you go through the whole suction
um as you teach a meditation be
sensitive to the fact that people's
attention degrades quickly in half an
hour
people's focus drops every minute during
a meditation it's very hard especially
in the era of the internet and cell
phones for people to focus and they get
tired meditating so you have to move the
meditation along you can't go slow you
can't go too slow you will lose the
people's attention people who live on a
cellphone can't focus more than a few
minutes so be aware of that and be
careful not to take the whole time with
the Suk Jong and then you don't have
time to meditate okay the next part of
Suk Jong is so far we did two big socks
well three we invited our teacher that's
a good scene we admired something about
them which is a mental prostration and
then we made offering to them of the
best offering which is the small
improvements in our own behavior I think
if you're like me when you report your
improvement to your teacher during the
offering you automatically think about
all the things you didn't improve
and all the mistakes you made when I
make offering to my own teacher all I
can honestly say is I've made some small
improvements and that makes me aware of
all the mistakes I've made and I
continue to make year after year so the
next part of Suk Jong is not suck it's
Jung
it's admitting in a very honest and open
way not hiding anything because after
all it's it's all in the mind right we
it's not as hard as telling your teacher
directly things that you've done that
are bad but in the meditation suction we
can get in the habit of being totally
honest with our teacher so think of
mistakes you've made
continue bad habits that have lasted for
years or decades and just be honest with
your teacher and say look I'm sorry
and if I was stronger I could stop all
of them but I'm not and be honest about
your mistakes and negative attitudes
here we go
admitting your mistakes to anyone around
you is a powerful way to break those bad
seas
the next warm-up of sub Jung is really
what we call coffee meditation in the
DCI teaching and think about good things
you've done small improvements and you
can also think about cool things other
people are doing and offered them to
your teacher for me
the second warm-up Suk Jong which is
offering the highest offering is your
practice to me the second one and the
fourth one which is rejoicing about your
small successes your small improvements
to me they overlap so sometimes I think
of one small progress I've made and I
offer it in step number two and then
when I get to step number four I think
of a different one but for me they're
not to the two steps are not so
different from each other
what we found in DCI teaching 30,000
people every year what we found very
interesting is that this step is the
most difficult for almost every person
we meet people have a lot of trouble
admitting that they're doing some right
things we all like to brag we all like
to praise ourselves but we have trouble
when it comes time to loving ourselves
in a deep way and and admiring what
we're doing right we tend to focus more
on the mistakes we make so during this
sock Jung step number four try very hard
to think about how lucky you are all the
good things in your life you're here
meditating you are inside a holy
powerful lineage tsongkhapa and you have
so much hope and you are so fortunate
out of millions and millions of people
in this world hundreds of millions of
people you are special
so the great books always say don't do
it as Pride we're not talking about
pride pride says I'm the best meditator
in this room and nobody can meditate
like me pride compares themselves to
other people and we were in a shoulder
stand yesterday in undresses class and
he said of a cool thing he said you know
maybe you're gonna stare at other people
during the whole yoga class and compare
yourself to them but please don't do it
during the shoulder stand you'll hurt
your neck it's kind of funny that's
pride it's not pride to say to report to
your Lama I did my yoga yesterday it
wasn't that easy but I did it and I did
my meditation and I'm doing retreat at
Diamond Mountain holy diamond mountain
retreat center
I have a lot of mistakes some of them
are very old mistakes but I'm really
trying hard and I'm here and I'm happy
about it
so do some coffee Manatee it's very
powerful seeds for a good meditation ten
minutes from now
inside of here if you like as a change
of pace just to change things some days
you can think about cool things other
people are doing Oh Tim is working so
hard and jing-mei is working for many
years to help and you can rejoice in
other people's John and Connie teaching
so devotedly for so many years and Peter
and Maria teaching giving hope to so
many people in the russian-speaking
countries for example so you can also
rejoice in other people's good season
as a meditation teacher start speeding
up the steps towards the end because
again people's attention people's mental
power drops quickly during a half hour
of meditation at the end they are much
more tired
the next step of Sakyong and we're
almost finished and by the way as a
teacher it's a good strategy to tell
your students you're almost finished a
lot of yoga teachers will say I'll just
stay for one more second two more
seconds in the post then they keep you
in the post for another minute so it's
good to tell your students over almost
finished we're almost gonna take a break
we just got one or two more to go which
is true the next warm-up the next part
of sup Jung is to ask your teacher to
teach you keep teaching me okay never
stop teaching me I like to I like to
share with my students and my own
experience is the people who hurt me in
my life have taught me more than the
people who are nice to me it's when you
have trouble big trouble from another
person that you go deeper into your life
into your understanding of emptiness so
I'd like to share with my students that
if you ask for teaching publicly from
the world then in the next week you
might get a lot of new problems because
you asked for them because you asked for
teaching so as you ask for teaching
remember it's not all Dharma teaching
it's not all scriptures and meditations
your greatest teachers are the people
who cause you trouble
people who push you people who
who demand your time people who
criticize you so be careful during this
preliminary when you ask for teaching
beware remember the greatest teachings
are the greatest challenges and be
grateful to people who challenge you
again you can speed up the steps as you
as the students get tired mentally last
step we're gonna do today and then we'll
take a break
it's called asking the teacher to stay
in your life so it's very difficult
chemically to make enough good seeds to
meet your teacher probably a lot of
those seeds were collected by your past
life I have a friend he he said it
caused his past life Joe
he says Joe Joe created this teacher not
me my past life worked harder than I do
and they created this beautiful teacher
my job is to keep enough good seeds
going that the teacher doesn't leave me
or pass away or were separated so during
this last stop jump step we ask the
teacher please stay in my life and that
request if it's sincere creates enough
seeds to keep them with you and almost
nothing more sad in the world then when
a father or mother loses their child if
you talk to them they'll say I I was
hoping I would die before them and
there's maybe nothing more painful then
for a mother or father to lose their
child but to lose your teacher is harder
much much harder so we want to you know
stim sincerely this day
now we're ready to meditate and we're
gonna take a break here so you can open
your eyes and take a stretch
I'm going to declare an official PP
break after questions and answers okay
anybody have a question anybody want to
keep everybody from the bathroom
nope okay David don't feel guilty okay
yeah I would I would have to suggestions
and they both come from Scripture okay I
guess to me the most important one is is
you know and I feel cool sharing I've
been trying to do all this stuff for 45
years 50 years you know and it it's
sweet to give you you know tips that I
learned one tip I learned is focus on
their presence and not on their color
and ship okay so it's actually more
important that you just feel their
presence then that you get the word on
their nose correct you see it I mean so
I think when a meditation teacher tells
us to bring the teacher where we're
trying very hard to get the color and
the shape and then we got to keep that
going while we do this other stuff and
it gets stressful inside the meditation
and then we feel guilty that's a third
thing that we're not getting the color
right you know
and the teachers melting on the left
side and oh my god I'm supposed to be
offering you know and then the whole
thing gets addressed for the meditation
is supposed to be peaceful but it
becomes stress it's like juggling a lot
of balls you know so yeah for sure I
think you're totally right you're
totally your instincts are totally right
don't worry so much about the color and
the shape and the eyes okay that's not
the point the point is the presence of
the person maybe you want to meditate
that they're behind you and you can't
see them and they're just like you know
and you just feel them in the room
okay and that's enough okay that's the
important thing
it's the heart connection with them
there's another suggestion in the long
room somewhere that just start with your
outline if you know the story of how the
Wheel of Life was painted for Audriana
they they held up a sheep and they built
a fire behind the Buddha and they just
did his silhouette his outline okay so
that's fine some meditation books say
just get the outline right and don't
worry about the rest you know like the
silhouette and then some meditation
books say the outlines not the main
thing the loving eyes are the main thing
so if it's just two eyes floating there
but with great love
they say that's more important than
getting their toes right in there you
know elbow right and because they are
that becomes stressful and then you
can't focus on the other stuff so yeah
feel happy about it get their presence
right that they're in the room believe
that they're in the room
and that's the important thing not the
colors and the shapes
okay any other peepee blockers
[Music]
okay
so I'll talk about that first and I just
want to repeat that the scriptures to
say keep the if you crack your eyes open
keep them at the nose so a lot of people
are like this and I've heard many
teachers safes to do this and it's
completely wrong okay
it means at the plane of the nose and it
what it means is don't focus your eyes
it just means don't focus your eyes okay
when you're in high school and you meet
that cute guy and you go home you're
like and you're not looking at anything
that's what we want that's what we want
so it's just like you know and I'll give
you a personal tip this carpet for
example is we call Paisley it's a flower
design from France I guess I don't know
Italy and it's very destructive so in
your meditation space just have plain
colors and the altar cloth in front of
you should just be plain colors okay and
for me when I do a retreat you know if
you're a serious retreat person let's
say you do two between a year a week or
a month and
depending on what just doesn't get you
fired at your job and you'll you'll find
you it's not enough to be a good
meditator you have to be a good retreat
house finder and it's not easy it's
probably not a good idea to do retreat
in your own apartment or your own home
there's too much history so it's really
ideal if you can go out into nature to a
place that's super quiet I was trying to
make noise yesterday because it was too
quiet in my cabin you know I was getting
uncomfortable and try to find a place
but my suggestion is the first thing I
do when I get to a new retreat Kevon is
I box up all the books and magazines I
anything that has writing on it
I I get it out of my sight because when
you're meditating when I'm meditating
I'm a book person so I if I see a book
or a magazine you know I'll read it we
used to have fights in through your
retreat for the cereal boxes because we
didn't have any books we decided the
first year we wouldn't have any books
except for our prayer books and then we
were really hungry to read something and
we all were reading the cereal boxes
like how many vitamins and how you know
it was so interesting so my first
suggestion is if you do crack your eyes
open okay keep it down okay but keep
your chin level okay so when you look
down don't go like this cuz you'll get
tired okay you'll get tired so if you do
open your eyes which is fine
crack them and point them down but don't
let your chin come down because that
will be a tendency you know when you
lower your eyes your head goes
okay so keep your chin level keep your
eyes down it's kind of like all those
Buddhist studies right he's like you
know maybe that's maybe he did the same
thing I don't know so anyway that's my
first suggestion it's about here yeah
anytime you feel tightness in your chest
or here my first thing I would say and I
think John and Connie people have done
long retreat don't let it go don't say
oh maybe it will be okay do something
okay cuz it will get worse if you're in
doing a lot of meditation it's a lung
it's a prana cheep-cheep blockage so
don't think it's gonna go away do
something okay
so what's a good way to take pressure
off of this edge in your chakra is to
smile okay and I know it sounds stupid
but most simple solutions are more
correct so small Mona Lisa's smile I'm
gonna go to France me and V are going in
May and you know everybody wants to see
the Mona Lisa in the Louvre and I mean
it's not very exciting but her smile is
cool and you know there's something
about it I think the artist was chose
not to drop a glass
anyway you'll figure that out so it
actually releases the termination point
of these ada and Pingala here if you
smile a little bit if you get tight if
your face gets tight it'll pull down the
chakra here here so that that will cause
a problem okay in general if you get a
check or a problem and by the way I'm
gonna take a peep next I don't care if
you have any questions that it'll be
normally it'll be here it's sometimes it
would be here
and don't forget this chakra is along
the spine it's in front of the spine so
you might feel some kind of discomfort
back here more than here but it could be
either place and traditionally if you
have a higher chakra tightening in your
meditation drop the focus to your navel
okay drop the focus to your navel navel
chakra doesn't mean they painted a
chakra on this little bump here that
your mom left you it doesn't mean that
navel chakra is in the back that navel
means at the level of the navel okay so
find your navel and go back and if
you're doing a visualization even your
teacher then don't put them in front of
you put them in your navel chakra put
them down here at the back okay and that
will draw prana away from these two
sensitive areas because and you must do
it you can't wait
you can't think it's gonna get better it
won't it'll get worse and worse and
you'll have to stop your meditation okay
I know people who damage these chakras
fifty years ago and it's still they
wrote me this week they're still having
trouble they they went to some teacher
who didn't
teach them properly they damage these
chakras and they're still having problem
fifty years later so don't let it go
okay it's like a leak in the bathroom do
something about it today okay don't wait
you know until it ruins the floor okay
it's one of those things you have to
work on right now okay drop it here drop
it to the back even the visualization
even the llama
even the teacher okay and that will help
a lot China okay as all the long-term
meditators know eating heavy oily foods
whatever is heavy and oily in your
culture I I don't know in our culture it
would be a piece of toast with half of
Cuba butter on it like half a pound of
butter butter is very good for lowering
your achi problem okay something greasy
have Mapo tofu with lots of oil
seriously something with lots of oil
okay and that helps also okay let's take
a pee-pee break yay okay then we'll
start Lam room
please come back at nine o'clock please
come back at nine o'clock